<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>O read me for I am of great antiquitie I       plaine Piers which can not flatter, a plough man men me call, my speech is      fowlle yet marke the matter now things may hap to fall, but now another Ile     haue for mee, I thinke it is as fit say, if any my name doo craue, I am the     gransier of Martin mareprelitte : compiled afore yeaster day, for the behoofe and ouerthrow of all parsons, vikars, and curats, who haue learned their cathechismes and can not yet vnderstand them, although they be past their grace.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19903A.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4823</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23935560</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23935560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09636)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1838:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>O read me for I am of great antiquitie I       plaine Piers which can not flatter, a plough man men me call, my speech is      fowlle yet marke the matter now things may hap to fall, but now another Ile     haue for mee, I thinke it is as fit say, if any my name doo craue, I am the     gransier of Martin mareprelitte : compiled afore yeaster day, for the behoofe and ouerthrow of all parsons, vikars, and curats, who haue learned their cathechismes and can not yet vnderstand them, although they be past their grace.</title>
                  <author>Roy, William, fl. 1527-1531.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Newly corrected ...</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[16+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed either of this side, or of that side of some the priestes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1589?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to William Roy--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacking all after signature D₂.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="mock_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>O Read me, for I am of great Antiquitie.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ I plaine Piers<note place="margin">
                     <add>the Ploughman</add>
                  </note> which can not flatter</l>
               <l>A plough man men me call</l>
               <l>My ſpeech is fowlle, yet marke the matter</l>
               <l>How things may hap to fall,</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But now another Ile haue for mee, I thinke it is as fit ſay, if any my name doo craue, I am the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ſier of Martin mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelitte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compiled afore yeaſter day, for the behoofe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of all Parſons, Vikars, and Curats, who haue learned their Cathechiſmes, and can not yet vnderſtand them, although they be paſt their grace.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Newly corrected, you will ſay it was by a gréene head, but Ile tell thée true,</l>
               <l>My head is neither gréene nor blew,</l>
               <l>You are deceiued <hi>bum fay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My head is either white or gray.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>So Beneado ſo:</p>
            <p>Printed either of this ſide, or of that ſide of ſome of the Prieſtes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26988:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26988:2"/>
            <head>To the puiſſant paltry politanes, bounſing Lord Biſhops, Popiſh parſons, Fickars, and Currats, with all that Romiſh rable, Piers, Grandſier of Martin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelate, wiſheth you better then I thinke you wiſhe your <hi>ſelues.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Yght reuiued ſirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>may it pleaſe your woorſhips fulneſſe to accept and reade ouer this worthy worke contayning in it very good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for that end that it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for, and ſurely how ſo euer ſome may miſlike it, bicauſe it toucheth their groſe corruptions, yet all thoſe that bee of a ſincere mynde will like it well, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe olde PIERS goeth ſoundly to worke, &amp; vſeth no flatterie, and hee ſayth nothing but he bringeth good proofes for it, therefore I am the more bolde to publiſhe it, taking you for my Patrons, vnder whoſe wynges in this good cauſe I ſhrowd my ſelfe, hoping that you will defend me, from all my perſicutors what ſo euer, for I knowe that you can keepe mee harmeleſſe if you pleaſe, and therefore I make choyce of you aboue any other, which if you doo, I ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:26988:3"/>
onely ſhewe my gr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> minde, theſe my firſt labours, which I pray you accept, but in time when I ſhall bee more able, you ſhall then here oftner from mee.</p>
            <p>Therefore hoping of your accuſtomed cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie and approoued protectorſhippe of this booke, I ceaſe to trouble you.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Surpliced Sirs farewell,</salute> 
               <signed>I can tell, my name full well.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26988:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26988:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>O Reade me for I am the annoynted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <p>I Piers plowman following plough on fielde my Beaſtes blowing for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brake my bod<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e requiring reſt, gaping for the gaine my labours gan me yeeld, vppon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Plough beame, to ſit me thought it beſt, [againe the haile I leaned, my face to H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auen I caſt, to that great Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, my buckler and my ſhield, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies after labours, ſendeth eaſe at the laſt, bicauſe I tell you plaine, without reſt naught can endure, this Lord him ſelfe firſt the darke did frame and made: Firſt of all prouiding the comfort of his Creature, before that thing earthlie his forme and ſhape did take, commaunding the night for euer all labours to abate, that wearie workemen all their bones might ſalue and cure, to ſerue t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God without ſtrife or hate: Then doth hee make the light for labours and buiſie care, the Firmament hee framed betwixt the waters twaine, the Seas, the earth, the hearbs, the trees, the fruits bright and faire, the Sunne, the Moone, the Starres for our profit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and gaine: the fiſhes in the floods, the birds in the ayre flowing: all kinde of beaſts, and man as Lord and ruler, then rayſeth hee
<pb facs="tcp:26988:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
eftſoones an Image to mans doo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, hee knew full well the labours to man more appoynted, though a whils of good &amp; bad not knowing, m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n lead a careleſſe life in innocencie then graunted, vnto the tyme vnto the time that Eue to the olde Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent aſſenting brought him into bondage vile labour and trauell, which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> night reſtrayneth the bodie ſore tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vnleſſe the womans ſeede be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ote <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our bale. This Seede to Noha than ſhadowed, releefe to no manne can finde, with comforte of the grape, and ſhip that ſaued ſome euen thoſe that him beleeued, and would not ſtill be blinde, all other then were drenched not regarding Gods doome by bringing Bull to yoake, yee brought in mikell eaſe, happie therefore be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, a ſainte he might be ſhryned, if euer poore ploughman of Pope might get the Keyes.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon it will be litle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, goods and life to daunger aye,</p>
            <p>Let them keepe from our houſes, &amp; ſhape vs no hoodes &amp; take this popiſhe playe.</p>
            <p>It is no article of my beliefe, though the prieſt hang it on his ſleeue &amp; publiſh it in courte an aſſyſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26988:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>It maketh me oft <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I my ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for my <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 paragraph">
                  <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>But let it goe, God <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> though new beleefes they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <p>Which haue all wold, in blindnes hold, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <p>Conſider O Kings and Princes, deere for you we toyle and laboure, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider I ſay eftſoones, now your flocke <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow that yee le<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de you ſhall made anſwers, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ill honour, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might yee <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>n Chriſts ſide, who is our guide and head, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> els your <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>et, &amp; ſharp to maintaine p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and how l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely a thing it is a chriſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Prince, to be Antichriſts protectour:</p>
            <p>We ſtriue not for the name whom all men hate for ſhame, for his forged days,</p>
            <p>The prieſts will him maintaine, ſo long as they haue poſſeſſion,</p>
            <p>Of them did he bring, to him will they bring, what ſo euer the hand can finde,</p>
            <p>Rather then he ſhould periſhed be, in his decrees and lawes cannon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26988:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Therefore doo they put downe, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the courſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of kinde</p>
            <p>Which would doo them good, with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, if they could take it ſo,</p>
            <p>To tell them <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t off that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, that h<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſinfull nation</p>
            <p>To bring them to light y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhineth bright, which the Scripture leadeth to.</p>
            <p>I heard a tale of late, how a Captaine <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, &amp; ſet a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <p>With many <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him about, who his conſent ſhould <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tter out, an <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> pride,</p>
            <p>His vncleane cage began to ſpeake, <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>deth open his beake <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I am that.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> knaues ſtanding <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, ſo and I, ſo am I, euerichone they crye.</p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> play y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſts withouten doubt al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaite,</p>
            <p>Marke their life, m<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke theſe learning, marke their order and euery thing,</p>
            <p>And yonge, yonge Popes they ben liche, they loſe, they binde,</p>
            <p>They haue both ſword and keyes, after the ſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e kinde that olde <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>afe had of late.</p>
            <p>I thanke my Lord God the liuing Lord for euer, that he hath giuen me grace to flea the Sodomi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, I was long in her lo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e,
<pb facs="tcp:26988:6"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:26988:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but I thanke my God the giuer, I haue eſcaped Sodome, and in God is my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, I ſpeake it of no rage, but as I will anſwere make, ſo their owne ſelues bee not Iudges, in their owne cauſe and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for then againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreadfull day, with cleare heart I will it vndertake.</p>
            <p>All this while mee thought I ſlept, but the boye can pricke his beeſt.</p>
            <p>Againe I take the plough in hande fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing mine honeſt labour,</p>
            <p>Till night commeth on, and ſunne go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g downe cauſeth me to ceaſe.</p>
            <p>In meane ſeaſon, I toſſe many thinges, as I were of porte and hauour,</p>
            <p>When I came home, all that night long, I could not ſleepe a winke,</p>
            <p>A booke therefore I tooke in hande, my ſelfe ſomething to eaſe.</p>
            <p>Wherein I wrote of ſundry ryte, as my heart dooth iudge and thinke.</p>
            <p>Aboute three yeares paſt when I Piers ſcripture might reade,</p>
            <p>And render and r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>porte to my wyfe and to my barnes,</p>
            <p>It ſeemed then a goodly life, a houſhold then to keepe and feede,</p>
            <p>Both with broth and bacon, and breade
<pb facs="tcp:26988:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the Byble,</p>
            <p>To tell forth Chriſtes trade, and trade of our chriſtening,</p>
            <p>Before we were called chriſten, &amp; knew of Chriſte nothing</p>
            <p>Then was I ſir, then was I father, then was I ſhepheard and all,</p>
            <p>Then nothing fayled vnto my bidding, neither in boure nor hall,</p>
            <p>My wyfe for my wiſdome did counte me hee head, my childer their father,</p>
            <p>My ſeruaunts their ſire, then all did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay me in the feare of the Lord,</p>
            <p>More then for meade or hier, this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord.</p>
            <p>I dare recorde againſt the popiſh pries, which clatter in the Kirke,</p>
            <p>And cannot worke nothing that good is, which had deſpight in heart,</p>
            <p>That wee to Chriſte did ſtart, leauing their cumbred riddles,</p>
            <p>And cried as their Fathers did before, out, out alas,</p>
            <p>Therefore all the world followeth him, and his,</p>
            <p>Seeing vs of the lewde fee, breake into heauen ſo violently,</p>
            <p>Which they were ſory for, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herds
<pb facs="tcp:26988:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they recked nothing,</p>
            <p>Being occupied with other thinge, as gentlemen and other,</p>
            <p>For the fleſhly fathers coulde boaſt that none of the promiſes,</p>
            <p>Nor the Phariſies were founde faulty herein, but onely the raſcall ſort,</p>
            <p>That knew not the lawe, lined ſinfull and curſed therefore ſayd they plaine,</p>
            <p>Wee will haue it in againe, from theſe poore knaues,</p>
            <p>That are ſo wood, trowe theſe harlots pardy, that Chriſte wold with ſaue to die,</p>
            <p>For ſuch a prophane beggerly blood.</p>
            <p>But comfort yee yee plough man, Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers, Tylers, and cobblers.</p>
            <p>Chriſte our king was a poore man, as Zacharie before propheſied, and hee him ſelfe ſaith, that Foxes haue dennes, &amp; birds of heauen neaſts, and mans ſonne hath not, where to lodge his head. And hee bleſſed the poore men, ſo they bee poore in ſpirite, ſaieng that theirs is all readie the Kingdome of high Heauen, and wo be vnto the riche, for they haue their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte in this world. Chriſte ſaith againe in Marke, his words ſowen in rich mens hearts bringeth forth no fruite, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfulnes
<pb facs="tcp:26988:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of riches, and the buſineſſe of this worlde cloggeth it and marketh it fruiteleſſe, this knewe our Popiſh prel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates full well, when they finde that gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and buſie occupied marchauntes are ſober, diſcreete, and wiſe, they will not rayle, they will doo no ſkathe.</p>
            <p>But I will tell you a newe tale, goe to all yee riche of heapes,</p>
            <p>With all your horned prellates,</p>
            <p>Weepe and howie for the miſteries that ſhall come vpon you,</p>
            <p>If there be no other thing to lay in your way,</p>
            <p>This I am ſuer yee cannot denay,</p>
            <p>That yee haue lyued in delight &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, you haue fed at your hearts liking,</p>
            <p>As againſt the day of ſlaughter,</p>
            <p>Yee haue condempned &amp; ſlaine the Iuſt, and hee hath not reſiſted you.</p>
            <p>Remember that terrible example of the riche man, and poore Lazarus. And I ſay againe to you poore caitiffes, there is an other world beſide this, and we can pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently abide the Lords woorking, there is no ſeede can bring great gaine but he be deed, this wee ſee playne in our yearely ſowing, beſide this we patiently abide vii.
<pb facs="tcp:26988:8"/>
monethes long, tho wee ſuffer at home much hunger and wrong, our whete or wee can gather why ſhould we not than, Gods woorking ken in ſauing vs with them: yea heare me deere brethren hogge-herds, ſheepeheads, and all your ſorte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, hath not God choſen the poore of this world, to be riche in faith, and heires of the kingdome, which he promiſed to all them of whom he was loued, that how can your byſhops hate then thus poore, and be the Apoſtles ſucceſſors, for they did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the poore all with theſe &amp; like words, as they can fall againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riche in towers, are they not the riche that exerciſeth their tiranny vpon you, and they haile you to their iudgment ſeates, &amp; the ſame are they that ſpeake euill of that good name which is named vpon you. Paule calleth them Idolators only bicauſe they gape ſo much vpon goods. And Chriſt him ſelfe ſaith, no man can ſerue two maiſters, both God &amp; riches. And againe, it is hard for a riche man to enter into heauen, as a Camill to goe through a needells eye, yet dooth the prieſtes flatter them, &amp; ſay that they onely may haue Gods word, which is called his kingdome, that they altogether may play
<pb facs="tcp:26988:9"/>
the part of cut my curre, that keepeth my Fother ſafe, which neither will eate any Haie himſelfe, nor ſuffer any cattell that breaketh looſe, to eate any thing thereat: thus doo they all conſpire againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, and his Chriſte.</p>
            <p>The biſhoppes giueth bribes, to holde Chriſte downe.</p>
            <p>And vp ſtart y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knights of the ſepulcar.</p>
            <p>This ſheweth that they haue the faith of Chriſte in vaine opinion,</p>
            <p>Or els would they iudge Chriſtes flocke a right, without regarde of perſon.</p>
            <p>Alas, doo yee not ſee that Chriſte will not be kept in graue,</p>
            <p>How longe doo you ſtriue againſt the ſtreame and ſpurne againſt the pricke,</p>
            <p>What haue you woon this xxx. yeeres, by putting to ſilence</p>
            <p>The word of God, and the maintayners thereof.</p>
            <p>It ſpringeth and ſpreadeth by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, like the Palme tree, that cannot bee ouercomne with burden, all though you treade it vnder your feete, and iudge it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthely, at length it ſhall beate downe you and condempne you, both great and ſmall to endles dampnation, &amp; lay vpon
<pb facs="tcp:26988:9"/>
your necke al the innocent blood, that hath ben ſpilt ſince Stephen the firſt Martyr, to this day, through your default, &amp; all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſhall follow after to the worlds end. Moyſes, by the mouth of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded thus, that we take heede leaſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we looſe our ſoule, forgetting the woonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous works that he hath wrought in the daies heretofore, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall publiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth ſtill, to our children &amp; poſteritie for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Againe he ſaith,<note place="margin">Note Deutro. Chapt.</note> the wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I doo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde this day, ſhalbe vpon thy heart, thou ſhalt reherſe them vnto thy children, and ſpeake of them when thou ſitteſt in thy houſe, when thou walkeſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, when thou goeſt to ſleepe, when thou riſeſt again then ſhalt thou binde them as a ſigne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy hand, and they ſhalbe a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance betwixt thine eies, thou ſhalt write them vpon the poaſtes of thy houſe, and in thy gates, that thy GOD bee at no time forgotten, for all they which coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it not good to knowe God, be they prieſts, be they princes, God giueth them vp into a reprobate minde, to doo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things that are not comly, filled with all vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſnes, fornication, craft, couetouſnes, &amp;c. But our prieſts are wiſer than Moyſes,
<pb facs="tcp:26988:10"/>
then Chriſte,<note place="margin">Note Phillip Chapt.</note> or his Apoſtles, for they were glad when by any maner of meanes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell was publiſhed, were it by contention or other waies: ſaith Paule, Philip. and where as Iohn was carnall,<note place="margin">Note</note> marke, and ſaith, we haue found a man caſting out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells in thy name, but wee haue forbidden him bicauſe he followeth not vs, and of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perchance forbid vs to name Chriſt in his worde, Chriſte him ſelfe anſwereth plaine: forbid him not, for no man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth any thing in my name, can ſtraight ſpeake euill of me: but our prelats cleane contrarie, to hinder Gods woord will not ſticke to die, bicauſe it vttereth their hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and deſtroyeth their papiſtrie, &amp; the Antichriſtian Idolatry: Heare yee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O yee Princes, and vnderſtand yee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iudge the earth, heare I ſaie &amp; feare, for you being officers of his kingdome, haue not executed true iudgement now of late, you haue not kept the law of rightiouſnes, nor called after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will of God: horrible, &amp; that right ſoone therefore, ſhall he appeere vnto you, for an hard iudgement ſhall they haue that beare rule. Mercie is graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the poore, but they that be in auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie, ſhalbe ſore puniſhed, wherefore ſet your</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26988:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
